啊
Ah.
来吧
Come on.
看着我
Look at me.
他去哪里了
Where'd he get to?
我不知道
I don't know.
不
No!
拿绳子来
Get the rope.
我们 向东前往印第安领地
We's... headin' east, towards Indian territory.
他的状况不好
He's in a bad way.
这就是你要说的全部吗
Is that everything you have to say on the matter?
我发誓 我发誓
I swear. I swear!
你知道吗
You know what?
我相信你
I believe you.
喔 达根
Whoa. Duggan.
喔
Whoa.
什么鬼
The hell?
你他妈是怎么知道
How the hell you figure this wound up
这片草地里有这东西的
out here in the middle of these grassland?
这真不错
This will work out nice.
放我走
Just cut me loose.
你再也不会见到我 真的 放我走吧
You'll never see me again, honest. Just cut me loose.
坐起来
Sit on up.
好吧 听着 我可以放了你
Well, you see, I would cut you loose,
但这会违背我对正义的坚持
but that just violates my sense of what's right.
老 亨 利
很难分辨一个人是谁 是什么人
It can be hard to tell who and what a man is,
他有足够能力可以说服你
he's got a mind to convince you otherwise.
我的族人来自我出生的纽约
My people were from New York, where I was born.
我三岁的时候
By the time I was three,
我们来到堪萨斯州科菲维尔
we'd made it to coffeyville, Kansas,
然后是亚利桑那州和新墨西哥州
then down to Arizona, then new Mexico.
我曾在墨西哥呆过一段时间
I was in Mexico proper for a time.
我做过很多种职业
I've tried my hand at many a vocation.
有些职业的收入更低
Some more marginal than others.
最后 我决定做一个农民
Finally, I settled on the life of a farmer.
这就是我
Which is what I am.
俄克拉荷马于1907年加入美国联邦 成为第46个州
俄克拉荷马准州 -1906
我们要储备猪饲料
We got that hog, stock to feed,
把地窖装满
and a root cellar to fill.
现在有拖拉机可以在很短时间做完这些
There's tractors can do this now in quarter the time.
是这样吗
Is that right?
我认为这里
And here I thought
怀亚特 种田是你的本份
farming was in your bones, Wyatt.
这里对你来说是个养家的好地方
This would be a good place for you to raise a family of your own.
我知道你妈妈会这么想的
I know your ma would have felt that way.
我不是她
I ain't her.
或他
Or him.
“人以智慧建造房屋”
By wisdom is a house built,
出自《圣经·箴言》 第24章第3节
“以聪明使它立得稳固”
and through understanding is it established.
“藉知识把房间充满各样”
Through knowledge are its rooms filled
“珍奇美丽的宝物”
with rare and beautiful treasures.
“那些一心朝圣的人是有福的”
And blessed are those hearts that are set on pilgrimage.
尽管我想留下来
Much as I'd like to stick around...
听你们互相引用圣经
Listen to y'all quote scripture at each other...
我要去打鸟了
I'm goin' bird huntin'.
谢谢你帮我 艾尔
Thanks for the help, al.
很高兴来这里
It does me good to be here.
不知何故 这里仍然让我觉得与玛丽有联系
Makes me feel like I'm still connected to Marie somehow.
帮你舅父收拾一下东西
Give your uncle a hand with his things.
前提是你已经休息好了
That is, if you've had sufficient respite.
谢谢你 孩子
Thank you, son.
好的 舅父
Yes, sir.
我今天早上准备去打猎
Yeah, I wanted to go huntin' this mornin',
但你爸说他需要帮忙
but your pa said he needed some help.
我当然想有一天和你一起去
Sure would like to go with you one of these days.
我觉得这不太合适
I don't think that'd go over too well.
你爸是个好人 怀亚特
Your pa's a good man, Wyatt.
否则我也不会让妹妹嫁给他了
I wouldn't let him marry my sister if I didn't think so.
用不了多久 你就可以
Soon enough, you'll be able to
随心所欲去旅行和打猎了
do all the travelin' and shootin' you want to.
别再纠结这个
Stop frettin' about it.
我们晚饭吃两块排骨 其余的熏制起来
We'll take two chops for supper and smoke the rest.
我没时间打理这些
I ain't got time to render this.
扔到猪舍里
Throw it in the pen.
你不觉得难受吗 它们吃自己
Don't it bother you sometimes, they eat their own?
对猪来说没什么区别
Don't make no difference to a hog.
你为什么住在这里
Why'd you settle here?
是什么意思
What's that meant to mean?
为什么在准州 不是别的地方
Why? Why the territory, of all places?
因为可以主张所有权
You could stake a claim,
指1889年4月 俄克拉荷马准州发生的“圈地潮”
持续使用一年 它就是你的了
hang onto it for a year, it was yours.
在当时似乎是个不错的交易
Seemed like a pretty good deal at the time.
你知道的 必须在枪响前赶到这里
Got here before the guns went off, you know that.
我还是不信这就是你想要的
I still don't believe this is what you wanted.
黎明时分起床 喂牲口 收割庄稼
Up at dawn, feedin' the stock, workin' the crops.
无论热还是冷 雨或晴
Hot or cold, rain or shine.
你会发现有更糟糕的安排
You'll discover there's worse arrangements.
爸爸
Pa?
放松 姑娘 就这样
Easy, gal, that's it.
我在你这么大的时候
Had me a mare near just like this
就像这样靠近过一匹母马
when I wasn't much older than you.
看这里
Lookie here.
你觉得发生了什么 是抢劫吗
What do you think happened? Some kind of robbery?
-枪战 -别乱说
-A shootout? -Shut your nonsense.
我最好去找那个骑手
I'd best go look for the rider.
好的 我去装马鞍
Yeah, I'll go saddle up.
你看好这匹马 待在里面等我回来
You tend to this horse and stay inside till I get back.
但如果有麻烦呢 爸爸 我可以帮你
But what if it's trouble, pa? I can help you.
继续 照我说的做
Go on. Do as I say.
喂
Hello.
不好
Nope.
怀亚特
Wyatt!
-他还活着吗 -还有口气
-Is he alive? -Barely.
他一个人吗
Was he alone?
是的 但那里还有其他人的踪迹
No, but I dispatched with a dozen others was there.
帮我一把
Give me a hand.
他 他失血过多
He's... he's lost a lot of blood.
他还能活吗
Is he gonna live?
我想取决于我们
Be up to us, I suppose.
现在太晚路又远 没法去找医生
Too far and too late to fetch the doc.
我去 如果必要 可以连夜赶路
Well, I can go. Ride all night if I have to.
我相信你可以
I'm sure you would.
所以
So?
你就呆在这里 把那瓶金缕梅给我
You'll stay right here. Hand over that witch Hazel.
他是个亡命徒
That is an outlaw.
在奔跑中摔下了马
On the run, shot off his horse.
你觉得他杀过人吗
You think he killed somebody?
怀亚特 我知道的跟你一样多
Wyatt, I know just as much as you do.
那是做什么
What's that for?
把伤口扎紧 以免他夜里失血太多
Seal the wound tight so he don't bleed out overnight.
不 胸部受伤千万别抬高双脚
No! Don't never elevate the feet with a chest wound.
我看到了你身上的伤疤
I've seen the scars on your body.
因为我没有对你隐瞒
'Cause I ain't hid'em from you.
现在也许你明白你的成长经历了
Now maybe you'll understand your raisin'.
来压住这里
Put your hand right here.
你要去哪里
Where you goin'?
在我回来前一直压着
Just keep applyin' pressure till I get back.
现在做什么
What now?
子弹必须出来 不然他会死
Bullet's gotta come out. And he won't make the ride.
分开绳子
Half that rope.
我去找医生
I'll fetch the doc.
你留在这里看着他
You'll stay here and keep an eye on him.
你真的觉得有必要吗
You really think that's necessary?
有必要
It ain't not necessary.
你为什么不冷静下来
Now, why don't you cool his fever
而不是为你
instead of vaporizin' on every
脑子里的想法感到自豪
thought that comes into your head?
没有痕迹
Trail's cold.
我们会抓住他
We'll get him.
那家伙能在水中追踪鱼
That dog could track a fish through water.
走吧
Come on.
如果他醒了 你要保持距离
He should come to, you keep your distance.
没事 他被绑住了
It don't matter he's tied up.
我自己能处理
I can handle myself.
照我说的做 我会尽快回来
You just do as I say. I'll be back soon as I can.
走吧
Come on.
比利在哪里
Where's Billy at?
是谁
低下头 你会没事的
Keep your head down. You'll be all right.
哇
Whoa.
他来过这里
He was here.
我不这么认为
Don't look like it to me.
如果我没猜错 他不是一个人
If I'm right, he weren't alone.
不管是谁都知道他做了什么
Whoever it is knows what he's doin'.
他像其他人一样很好的掩盖了行踪
Covered his tracks as good as anyone I've run across.
要不是这场雨 我早就找到他了
Weren't for this rain, I'd have found him sooner.
我不需要听你那愚蠢的
I don't need you to speechify the inner workings
狗脑子是如何推测的
in your halfwit canine mind.
我只想知道他在哪里
I need to know where he's headed.
嗯 这并不能缩小搜索范围
Well, that don't exactly narrow it down.
我在哪里
Where am I?
你到底是谁
Who the hell are you?
我爸爸发现你 快死了
M-My pa found you, close to dead.
他把你带回来了
He brought you back here.
噢 是吗
Oh, yeah?
你爸爸是谁
Who's your pa?
普通人 呃
Nobody. Uh...
亨利 就是个农民
Henry. Just a-a farmer.
什么 这里只有你和他
What, it's only you and him here?
他现在在吗
He here now?
他就在后面
He's just out back.
在喂猪
Tendin' to the hogs.
噢 是吗
Oh, yeah?
好吧 去叫他来
Well, go fetch him.
不要 动
Quit mov... moving!
好了 我不想伤害你
Right now, I don't want to hurt you.
我不想伤害你 别动
I don't want to hurt you. Stop moving!
你把我的枪和包放哪儿了 听我说
Where'd you put my gun and my satchel? Listen to me!
我不知道你在说什么 先生
I don't know what you're talkin' about, mister.
别骗我
Don't you lie to me!
你拿我的枪和包做什么
What'd you do with my gun and my satchel?
爸爸
Pa!
他是怎么逃脱的
How'd he get loose?
他扭动着挣脱了
H-He wriggled free.
挣脱的
Wriggled free?
他拿到我留在床头柜上的刀了
And got hold of my knife I left on the bedstand.
我们两个都有责任
Well, that's on the both of us.
帮我把这混蛋绑起来
Help me tie the son of a bitch back up.
好吧
Okay.
你最好仔细想想你自己惹的麻烦
You better think long and hard on what you got yourself into.
有趣 我正要对你说同样的话
Funny, I was about to tell you the same thing.
你想拿它做什么
What you aimin' to do with that?
把你身上的子弹取出来
Gonna dig that bullet out of you,
也许在这过程中会得到些答案
maybe get some answers in the process.
听到我想听的
I like what I hear,
我也许会给你点减轻痛苦的东西
I might be inclined to give you something to ease the pain.
不
No.
No!
好吧 听着 听着
Okay! Listen, listen!
不
No!
从你告诉我你是谁开始
Let's start with you tellin' me who you are.
我是执法人员 是个警察
I'm law! I'm a goddamn lawman!
他不是警察 爸爸 他想杀了我
He ain't no lawman, pa, he was fixin' to kill me.
想喝点威士忌吗
Ready for some whisky?
我说了 我是执法人员
I just told you... I'm law.
问他钱的事
Ask him about the money.
什么钱
What money?
他问过我这个
He asked me about it.
听着 听我说
Listen. Listen to me.
好把 听着
Okay, listen.
一个拿着满满一包现金的警察在干什么
What's a shot lawman doin' with a satchel full of cash?
听着
Listen!
听着 如果你还有脑子
Listen! If you got a brain in your head,
你就必须带上你的孩子
you need to get yourself and your boy
尽快离开这里
out of here fast as you can.
听到了吗
You hear me?
不
No.
噢 不 不 不
Oh, no! No, no!
至少在我找到想知道的之前
At least we know you won't die
你一时还死不了
'fore I find out what I want to know.
噢 上帝
Oh god.
给我再喝点
Let me have a little more.
让我
Let me...
有骑手
Riders.
拜托 放开我 快 放开我
Come on, cut me loose. Come on, cut me loose.
听着 他们可能有三个人
Listen, they gon' be three of'em.
一个是墨西哥人
One's a Mexican.
另一个是留着大胡子的
The other's an ugly son of a bitch
丑八怪
with a thick beard.
而他们的头
And their leader...
他们的老大看起来是个你不想惹的人
Their leader looks like a man you don't want to mess with.
相信我 你不会想惹
And believe me, you don't.
不要靠近窗户
Keep back from the window.
如果你们想活命 就放开我
If you want to live, you gotta turn me loose
把枪给我 听到了吗
and give me my gun, hear?
他在撒谎
He's lyin'.
我说了退后
I said keep back.
照做
Go on.
我能帮你们吗
Can I help you?
我是萨姆·凯彻姆警长
I'm sheriff Sam ketchum.
他们是我的副手
These here are my deputies.
我们一直在追踪一个逃犯
We've been scoutin' for a man on the run.
他最近自称叫柯里
Lately goes by the name of curry.
被击伤了
Been shot.
六英尺高 棕色头发 据说很帅
Six foot, brown hair, said to be handsome,
尽管大多数人都觉得他只是个小混混
though most would want him credited for nothing but devilry.
但我知道 他很危险
What I do know is, he's dangerous.
你看到这附近有这些特征的人吗
You seen anybody around here answers that description?
你说你是警长 我怎么不认识你
Say you're a sheriff? How's it I don't recognize you?
我们从伍兹县那边来的
We're from way over in woods county.
我们现在要找的柯里
Now, this curry we're looking for,
他在密苏里州和
he's got a warrant on him there
田纳西州都有逮捕令
in Missouri and Tennessee.
他可能自称是执法人员
Might also claim he's the law.
他曾经玩过这种把戏
He's got a history of such chicanery.
但远非如此
Far from it.
他是个杀手
He's a killer.
他会再次杀人
He will kill again.
你不会用那把枪
You're not fixin' to shoot
朝我们射击吧 是吗
any of us with that pistol, are you?
目前我没理由这么做
So far I got no reason to.
是个好消息
That's good news.
农夫 在你举起那把枪前得想清楚
You'll want to think'fore you raise that thing up, farmer.
没什么好担心的 朋友
Nothing to be worried about here, friend.
只是我正在做的一个小东西
Just a little project I'm working on,
仅此而已
that's all.
有多少人住在这里
How many people live out here?
这和你有什么关系
What difference is that to you?
我只是想确定你是安全的
I'm trying to make sure you're safe, is all.
这似乎不归你管
Wouldn't seem to be your business,
因为你是从伍兹县来的
seeing as how you're from woods county.
你结过婚
You married?
我看见那边有一座坟墓
Saw a grave over there.
是我妻子
My wife.
十年前死于肺结核
Died ten years back from tuberculosis.
节哀顺变
My condolences.
可怕的离开方式
Horrible way to go.
爸爸 告诉他们
Tell'em, pa. Tell'em!
墓上刻着 玛丽·霍布斯·麦卡蒂
Marie hobbs mccarty, the marker said.
你姓麦卡蒂
Your last name mccarty?
没错
That's right.
名字呢
First name?
亨利
Henry.
我猜霍布斯是她的族人
So hobbs was her people, I'm guessing.
因为我看到东边有个霍布斯农场
'Cause I noticed a hobbs ranch to the east of here.
是她的兄弟
Her brothers.
嗯
Uh-huh.
嗯 从这些东西来看
Well, from the looks of things,
你在这里已经住了多年
you've been out here a good many years.
环境不错
Nice situation.
都依偎在这群山中
All nestled up here in the hills.
从远处很难发现
Hard to see from a distance.
这跟你要找的那个人有什么关系
What's any of this got to do with the man you're lookin' for?
关系不大 我承认
Not much, I'll Grant you.
很久以前 呃
Long time ago, uh...
一个人在新墨西哥州和亚利桑那州惹了些麻烦
Was a fella caused some trouble down Arizona, new Mexico way.
听说他叫麦卡蒂
Heard he went by the name mccarty.
我想知道他是否是你的亲戚
I was wondering if he might be your kin.
你找错人了
You got the wrong pig by the ear.
意思是
Meaning?
除了这里 我不认识任何地方的麦卡蒂
I don't know no mccartys anywhere but here,
我所有亲戚都死了
and all my kin is deceased.
现在我要做晚饭
Now I got chores to tend to
木柴不够 我要干活去了
and scant wood to cook my supper.
我没见过你要找的人
I ain't seen the man you're after.
我会保持警惕
I'll keep my eyes peeled.
如果我在切克沙见到他
Be sure to alert the good sheriff
肯定会通知好警长
in chickasha if I should run across him.
那好吧
Well, then.
谢谢你的帮助
I thank you for your help.
看起来又是条死胡同 孩子们
Looks like another dead end, boys.
你今晚一定要关好门
You be sure to lock your doors tonight.
注意安全
Stay safe.
走吧
Come on.
现在你想用这个了吗
Now you're inclined to hang onto that?
我想你可能需要帮助
I thought you might be needin' help.
你想告诉我这是怎么用的吗
You wanna tell me how this got fired?
我会用 爸爸
Honest, pa.
别骗我
Don't you lie to me!
我知道它如何使用
I wanted to know what it's like.
我是50英里内唯一一个从未开过枪的男孩
I am the only boy for 50 miles that's never fired one.
你甚至不让我碰你的旧猎枪
You won't even let me lay hand on your old shotgun.
所以你不教我射击 我只能自己学
So if you can't teach me proper, I gotta do it myself.
如果你再动我的枪 我就揍你
You get into my things again, I will crack your crust!
你就是个又蠢又没用的老头
You're a stupid, worthless old man.
一辈子除了守着这破农场
A whole life, and nothin' to show for it
根本碌碌无为
but this rundown old farm
还有一个会离开你 让你孤独老死的男孩
and a boy who's gonna leave you alone to die as soon as he's able.
让我猜猜
Let me guess.
你会告诉我他不是伍兹县的治安官
You gon' tell me that he ain't the sheriff of woods county, you are.
他们不是 他们是银行劫匪
They ain't lawmen, they're bank robbers.
好吧 他们干了些什么
Well, what's left of them, anyway.
抢劫了亚当斯快车
Knocked over the Adams express.
我和副手追上去杀了其中两人
Me and my deputies gave chase, killed two of'em,
包括那个携带赃款的人
including the one carrying the loot.
银行劫匪戴着徽章
Bank robbers wearin' badges?
他们从我们这里偷的
That they took off me and my men.
他是冒充执法人员
He's the one impersonating the law.
但是你把钱拿走了
But you made off with the money.
见鬼 是的 我拿了
Hell, yeah, I grabbed it.
那你为什么不带着钱回伍兹县
Then why ain't you back with it in woods county?
噢 不知道 为什么必须这么做
Oh, I don't know. Why does it look like?
我的首要任务是
And my first priority was
活着逃离那伙人
getting away from that bunch alive.
这就是为什么我拼命跑 直到晕倒
That's why I rode like hell till I couldn't no more.
我记得的最后一件事 就是在这里醒来
There's the last thing I remembered, till I woke up here.
听着 我知道这些话对你来说都很荒谬
Look, I know what I'm saying sounds ridiculous to you and all.
确实如此
That it does.
我不知道他们刚才为什么没开枪杀了你
Why they didn't shoot you dead on the spot just now, I don't know.
但我可以向你保证
But I can guarantee you...
他们会回来的
They'll be back.
我唯一不明白是
Only thing I can't figure
那老头为什么会为一个陌生人冒生命危险
is why the old man would risk his neck for a stranger.
也许他得到了一笔钱
Maybe he got offered a cut of the money.
有些迹象表明不是这样
Something tells me that ain't it.
我们谁都可以干掉他
Any one of us could have taken him out.
这就是我们现在该做的
Which is what we should do now.
-马上行动 -还不行
-Ride up, finish it. -Not just yet.
因为那个东倒西歪的老农
'Cause of some shaky old farmer?
他不像我见过的任何农民那样拿枪
He didn't hold that pistol like any farmer I've ever seen.
我们有三个人
There are three of us.
我们不会抢银行 也不会不了解情况
We don't run up in a bank, or ride up on a stage
就去抢劫驿站
without knowing who's in it.
但我们知道柯里带着钱在房子里
We know curry's in there. With our money!
这就是你要去侦察那个所谓农夫之家的原因
Which is why you're going to reconnoiter that so-called farmer's place
确保柯里还没有逃走
and make sure curry don't skedaddle.
很乐意
Gladly.
在我们到之前不要妄动
Don't make a move till we get there.
好的
Fine.
-达根 -我说很好
-Duggan. -I said fine.
明早日出时 你跟我去切克沙
Come sunup, you and me will head into chickasha,
雇几个枪手
hire some guns.
知道了
Understood.
途中我们顺带拜访农夫霍布斯
On the way, we'll pay a call on farmer hobbs...
看看他有没有关于
Find out if he's got anything interesting
老亨利·麦卡蒂的事要告诉我们
to tell us about ol' Henry mccarty.
怀亚特
Wyatt. Come on in.
进来吧
Come on in.
-我快做完了 -留到早上做
-I'm almost finished. -Leave it till morning.
快点
Come on.
如果我能自己吃饭 就更方便了
It'd be a damn sight easier if I could feed myself.
一点都不给你吃更方便
Be a damn sight easier not to feed you at all.
-我们曾经见过吗 -我会记得的
-You and me ever met? -That I'd remember.
你当警长多久了
How long you been a sheriff?
-到现在已经18年了 -你是怎么开始的
-I'd say onto 18 years now. -How'd you get your start?
我是大比尔·汤普森在斯特斯普陵的副手
I was a deputy for big bill Thompson in Baxter Springs.
斯特斯普陵 密苏里州
Baxter Springs. Baxter Springs, Missouri?
-堪萨斯州 -瘦个子 大耳朵
-Kansas. -Skinny fella, big ears?
很壮
Heavyset.
一个喝醉的矿工
Missing part of his left ear from
开枪打掉他一块耳朵
a drunk miner taking a potshot at him.
-我听说是个喝醉的妓女 -噢 是吗
-I heard it was a drunk whore. -Oh, you did?
你住在斯特斯普陵的哪个地方
Which part of Baxter Springs you live in?
一家旅馆 在格兰特驿站附近
A boarding house. Out near Grant's stage station.
女店主叫什么名字
What was the landlady's name?
她不是淑女
She weren't no lady.
她叫汉娜 是个讨厌的老太婆
She a nasty ol' cuss named Hannah.
你见过乔治·克鲁克吗
You ever run into a George crook?
你是说乔治将军
You mean general George?
这混蛋毕生致力于
Sumbitch dedicated his life
把印第安人赶出该地区
to driving the caddo out of the territory.
你到底是怎么来到斯特斯普陵的
How in the hell did you end up in Baxter Springs?
就像其他梦想着
Well, like every other fool
轻松挖矿发财的傻瓜一样
dreaming of easy riches and digging for tin.
直到我意识到根本是做梦
Till I realized there weren't none.
只不过是一堆关于烟山河矿区的传说
Just a bunch of ghost stories about a mine near smokey hill river.
然后我 我破产了 工作很难找
Then I... I was broke. Work was hard to come by.
我很幸运大比尔喜欢我
I'm lucky big bill took a liking to me.
否则我 我不知道我会怎么样
Otherwise I... I don't know what would have come of me.
很抱歉 我之前袭击了你儿子
I... I'm sorry I jumped your boy before.
我在一个陌生的地方醒来 不知道他是谁
I woke up in a strange place, didn't know who he was...
我以为在某个藏身处被扣为人质
I was being held hostage in some hideout.
你觉得这像个藏身处吗
This look like a hideout to you?
我无意中听到他之前说的话
I overheard what he said earlier.
他不是那个意思
He didn't mean any of that.
对 他不是那意思
Yes, he did.
我解开你一只手 别让我再绑起来
I'll give you one hand free. Don't make me take it off.
好吧
All right.
你父亲也是农民吗
Was farming what your daddy did?
我爸爸在我3岁时就死了 在堪萨斯州
My daddy died when I was 3, up in Kansas.
除了种地 他几乎什么都做
And he did near everything but work the land.
我15岁时成了孤儿
I was orphaned at 15.
比我成为孤儿的时间少了13年
That's 13 years longer than I knew my folks.
啊 你在哪里长大的
Ah. Whereabouts you grow up?
新墨西哥州
New Mexico.
-哪个地方 -萨姆纳堡
-Which part? -Fort Sumner.
土生土长 听说过那里吗
Born and raised. You heard of it?
比利小子被杀的地方 是吗
Where Billy the kid was shot, wasn't it?
那里就是因此闻名的
Main reason anyone know it.
事情发生当晚我就在那里
I was there the night it happened.
情况怎样
How's that?
我当时只是个孩子
I was just a boy.
我曾经为一个叫
I used to make what money I could
彼得·麦克斯韦的人做零工努力挣钱
doing chores for a fella by the name of Peter Maxwell.
彼得·麦克斯韦安排比利过夜
Same Peter Maxwell put the kid up for the night.
他同时也给加勒特及他的副手
Same Peter Maxwell tipped off Garrett
波和麦金尼通风报信说
and his deputies, poe and mckinney,
比利小子躲在那里
the kid was holed up there.
我正在打扫马厩
I was sweeping the stalls.
当我看到加勒特走进房子时 我
When I saw Garrett walk in the house, I...
我脑子里一片空白
I don't think nothing of it.
但比利不在里面 至少那时不在
But Billy wasn't in there. Not then, leastways.
-知道我怎么知道 -怎么
-Know how I know? -How?
在离我不到20呎的地方
He was barefoot in his shin sleeves,
他正赤脚挽起袖子
cutting the meat off a deer carcass
在鹿的身上切下肉
not 20 feet from where I was working.
我看见他从谷仓门往里偷看
I saw him peer through the barn door,
他看到了波和麦金尼在门廊上
and he saw poe and mckinney on the porch there.
他停止切肉 直视我的眼睛
He stopped carving, looked me dead in my eye.
他说 “低下头 你会没事的”
He said, "keep your head down, you'll be all right."
比利冲进麦克斯韦的房间
So Billy went straight to Maxwell's room,
他很快意识到不只是麦克斯韦在里面
realized pretty quick it ain't just Maxwell in there.
他喊道 “是谁 是谁 ”
He called out, "¿quien es? ¿quien es?"
因为比利的西班牙语说得和墨西哥人一样好
'Cause Billy spoke Spanish as good as a Mexican.
怎么回应的
Pat's answer?
开了两枪 一枪打偏 另一枪打中胸部
Two shots. One wide of the Mark, and the other one in the chest.
这就是比利小子的结局
That was the end of Billy the kid.
你都看到了
And you seen it all.
我确实看到了
I most certainly did.
也看到比利的尸体被拖走
Saw the kid's body get hauled off too,
裹在血淋淋的被单里
wrapped in a bloody sheet.
这让我意识到这不是我的生活
Enough to teach me that ain't no life for me.
我宁愿停止这种疯狂行为也不想陷入其中
I'd rather stop this crazy than be part of it anyway.
好吧
Well...
该死
Damn.
如果我知道一个好故事足以让你放我走
If I knew all it took was a good story for you to cut me loose.
你现在能坐稳马鞍吗
You well enough to stay upright in the saddle?
-应该可以 -我要你离开这里
-Not hardly. -I want you out of here.
我想等到黎明走不是个好选择
I suppose waiting till sunup ain't an option?
如果我一个人在这里 就不同了
If I was alone out here, it'd be different.
那么 我想我准备好了
Well, then, I guess I'm ready.
好的
Good.
拿去
Take it.
我去拿你的包
I'll fetch your loot.
-爸爸 -怀亚特 蹲下
-Pa? -Wyatt! Get down!
我想我没事
I-I think I'm all right.
他中枪了吗
Is... is he hit?
他只是昏过去了 给我枪
He just passed out. Give me that.
我用枪比你想象的好
I'm better with it than you think.
除非我教你正确的方法
Not until I teach you proper.
-我自学过了 -嘘
-I've taught myself -shush.
你们到哪里去了
Now, where'd you get to?
-他在房子下面 -嘘
-He's under the house. -Shh.
我希望你知道如何用这个
I hope you got good enough with this.
上帝不希望发生这种事 但开枪射人
God forbid it happens, but shooting a man
与射击靶子不同
is different than hitting a target...
一旦越线就回不来了
A line you can't cross back over.
我懂
I know that.
在你做过之前 你不会懂
You couldn't until you've done it.
如果他进来
If he comes in here...
你就扣动扳机
You pull that trigger.
瞄准胸部
Aim for the chest.
并连续开火直到击中
And keep firing until you hit it.
你要去哪里
Where you going?
狗杂种
Son of a bitch!
混蛋
Cocksucker!
妈的
Fuck.
该死
Shit.
其他人呢 他们在附近吗
Where's the others? They close?
去死吧
Go to hell.
这种方式我见得太多
I've been here too often to let
你这种人岂能瞒过我
a man of your caliber overhaul my baggage.
回答我 否则你现在就完蛋
Answer me, or it ends for you right now.
去死吧 你这混蛋
Go to hell, you bastard.
他想杀了我们两个
He was fixin' to kill us both.
我看见了
I saw.
他可能只是来侦查 然后想一人搞定
Probably here to watch and got greedy.
其他人会来的
The others will be coming.
首先 我们得把尸体处理掉
First thing, we gotta get rid of this body.
我们要怎么做
How we gonna do that?
你不用来
We ain't.
我知道这感觉不好
I know it don't feel like it.
你很幸运只是擦伤
You're lucky it just grazed ya.
如果你知道我找到了那把枪
If you know I found that gun,
你就知道我看到了壁橱后面的东西
you know I saw what's in the back of that closet.
你是谁
Who are you?
我就是我
I'm who I am.
你不是一直在说要诚实吗
Aren't you always preaching about being honest?
出自《圣经》
“真相将还你自由”
The truth will set you free?
我从来没有骗过你
I've never lied to you.
把整件事情告诉我不是一回事吗
Isn't not telling me the whole story the same damn thing?
我做了一些我希望能收回的事
I've done things I wish I could take back.
在有你之前很久 在有你妈妈之前
A long time before you. Before your ma.
你不该听到的事情
Things that you got no business hearing.
如果你不尊重我 我又怎么尊重你
How am I supposed to respect you if you ain't respecting me?
我尊重你
I am respecting you.
如果你不明白这点
And if you don't understand that,
那我刚才说的你一个字都没听见
you ain't heard a word I just said.
不 我听到了 我只是一点都不信
No, I heard it. I just don't believe a bit of it.
低下头
Keep your head down.
低下头 你会没事的
Keep your head down. You'll be all right.
你会没事的
You'll be all right.
喔
Whoa.
-早 -早
-Morning -morning.
-我能帮你什么吗 -我确实希望如此
-Something I can help you with? -I sure hope so.
你这地方真好 安宁 平静
Nice place you got here. Peaceful. Quiet.
打鸟
Bird hunting.
没什么能比得上打一群鸟更好了
Nothing quite like the flush of the bevy.
你肯定很擅长射击
You must be quite the shot.
尽力而为
Do what I can.
我很羡慕你
I envy you.
尽管我这几天很想
I don't get to go out hunting
但我没法出去打猎
as much as I'd like to these days.
先生 有什么能帮你的吗
Something I can help you with, mister?
我爸爸过去常打野鸡
My daddy used to hunt pheasant.
打理它们一直是我该死的事
It was always my damn job to clean'em.
噢 割开胸部皮肤 把它剥开
Oh, cutting the skin on the breast, peeling it back.
但做久了 我找到了去除内脏的
But over time, I figured the best way
最好的方法
to get rid of their innards...
就是把鸟的背劈开 就那么做
Was to split the bird's back. Get to'em that way.
你也这么发现的吗
Is that what you find?
听着 我不
Look, I don't...
我觉得不太礼貌 但是
Mean to be UN-neighborly, but...
开门见山吗 当然
But get to the point? Sure.
我想问你几个问题 呃
I wanted to ask you a couple questions about, uh,
是有关你妹夫的
your brother-in-law.
那么 你关心他什么
Well, what concern is he of yours?
这就是我想弄明白的
That's what I'm trying to figure out.
你看 我有个疯狂的想法
You see, I got this crazy idea...
对老麦卡蒂来说
There might be more to ol' mccarty
远比看到的更多
than meets the eye.
你应该是个执法人员之类的吧
You supposed be some kind of lawman or something?
差不多
Something like that.
我想你该走了
Well, I think it's time you left.
哦 我们来这里寻找一些答案
Well, we came here for some answers.
在找到答案前不会离开
We ain't leaving till I get'em.
是吗
That so?
我应该
I should...
现在我们怎么让他清醒过来
Now how the hell we gonna pick his ass up?
好吧 好的 谢谢
Okay. Okay, thank you.
天哪 好吧
Oh, god. Okay.
我无法旅行 我走不了
I'm no good to travel. I'm not.
你带着孩子 你们离开这里
You take the boy, you get out of here.
当凯彻姆和他的手下来时
When ketchum and his men arrive,
我会尽量拖住他们
I'll hold them off as long as I can.
-见鬼去吧 -怀亚特
-The hell with that! -Wyatt.
我们有枪
We got guns.
你已经徒手杀了他们中一个
You already killed one of them barehanded.
打个包 我们离开
Fill a pack. We're leaving.
我警告过你
I'm warning you.
他回来了
He's back.
剩下的留着吧
Leave the rest.
我们不能把他留在这里等死
We can't just leave him here to die.
我他妈肯定不会因为
I am damn sure not gonna lose you
一些与我们无关的事失去你
over something that ain't our fight.
你爸爸是对的
Your pa's right.
我已经长大了 可以自己决定
I am old enough to make my own decisions,
不管你是否愿意接受
whether you are ready to accept that or not.
这是我要解决的事
Yeah. This is mine to finish.
快走吧 我不会有事
Go on, now. I'll be all right.
喔
Whoa.
柯里
Curry!
家里有人吗
Anybody home?
你们需要什么吗
You gentlemen need something?
我们是来抓逃犯的
We're here for our fugitive.
我昨天告诉过你没见过他
I told you yesterday I ain't seen him.
我的直觉告诉我那不是真的
My intuition tells me that's not true.
我就直说了
I'll make it easy...
你把他交出来 我们就放过你和孩子
You hand him over, we let you and the boy go free.
另一个选择是 我们带走他
The other option is, we take him.
你和那个孩子死
And you and the boy die.
你接受这个交易
You take that deal.
这是我的事 不是你的
I signed up for this, you didn't.
看看你的马已经备好鞍了
See your horses are already saddled.
你们可以骑着它离开这里
You can just ride on out of here.
你和我都知道在我们上马前就会被杀
You and I both know we'll be dead before we mount our horses.
在这变成一场屠杀之前
Fore this turns into some kinda brigasee,
你我为什么不用决斗
why don't me and you settle this,
来解决问题
knuckle and skull.
你作为一个农民经常打架
You got a lot of fight for a farmer.
这种表演不是办法
That ain't the way this plays out.
把他带上来
Bring him up!
艾尔
Al?
听我说 有些事很快就会发生
Listen to me. What's gonna happen will happen quick.
我会尽量拖住他们 你悄悄溜出去
I'll stall long as I can, but I want you to sneak out back
躲到罗杰的磨坊里
and hole up at Roger's mill...
在那里等我
And wait for me there.
只有必要时才用这个
Only use this if you have to.
让我参战
Let me fight.
如果你留下会让我没法集中精力
I can't do this right if I'm worried about protecting you.
把我交出去
Just turn me over.
不然他们会杀了我们所有人
You don't, they're gonna kill us all.
你我都清楚 不管怎样他们都会杀了我们
You and me both know they're fixin' to do that anyway.
你觉得我能在枪战中安全离开吗
And yet you expect me to run out into sure gunfire?
你儿子说得对
Your boy's right.
呆在里面
Stay inside.
离窗户远点
Stay away from the window.
如果你必须开枪 瞄准胸部 然后
You have to shoot, aim for the chest, and...
继续开火 直到我击中
Keep firing till I hit something.
我一直都怀疑你什么来头 亨利·麦卡蒂
I've had some suspicions about who you are, Henry mccarty.
我承认
I got to admit,
这名字像根刺一样扎在我心里
that name sticks in me like a Thorn.
我的好奇心被勾起了
My curiosity was aroused.
我希望艾尔能给我们一些提示
I was hoping al here might shed some light.
但他拒绝说
He wouldn't say shit.
即使在我的人
Even after my boys were...
怎么说呢 呃 在他们的强烈要求下
What's the word? Uh, emphatic in their question.
你可能觉得我不是警长
You probably concluded I'm no sheriff.
这些人也不是我的副手
Nor are these men my deputies.
在一个月前 我们中没人去过伍兹县
Not a one of us had spent time in woods county before a month ago.
那你呢
What about you?
你来自哪里
Where'd you come from?
除了这里 世界上任何地方
Every place on earth but this.
就这样吧
So be it.
最后条件
Last offer.
为柯里治安官和钱
This tongue-tied piece of shit
准备的这堆口是心非的废话
for sheriff curry in there and the money.
你得到你想要的
You get what you want.
我得到我想要的
I get what I want.
我们各奔东西 没有流血
We go our separate ways without blood spilled.
不是你的 不是我的
Not yours, not mine.
也不是你那个男孩 我看到他透过
Not that boy of yours I see surveilling
窗户在监视这一切
all this through that window.
如果我想流血
If I wanted bloodshed,
我早就从那里破门而入了
I'd have busted in there guns a-blazin' a long time ago.
我相信你明白
I believe you know that.
你把我内兄留在原地
You leave my brother-in-law right where he is.
转身离开我的房子
Turn and ride your asses off my property.
你照做 我就让你活命
You do that, and I'll let you live.
你们听到了吗 伙计们
You hear that, fellas?
这是一个温和老农说的话吗
Is that the talk of a mild old sodbuster?
我想不是
I think not.
不是
Nah.
这听起来完全是另外一回事
That sounds like something else altogether.
霍布斯
Hobbs!
你能告诉我什么事可能改变这个僵局吗
Anything you could tell me might change the equation here?
来舔我屁股 你这唠叨的混蛋
Kiss my ass, you long-winded son of a bitch.
我再给你一次机会
You got a pair, I'll give you that.
最后机会 艾尔
Last chance, al.
你根本不知道
You have no idea
你将释放的是地狱风暴
the hell storm you fixin' to let loose.
请注意我的警告
Consider me properly warned.
冷静
Easy.
喔
Whoa.
冷静点 伙计
Easy, fella.
该死的
Goddamn.
看这个
Look at that.
她完成了
I'd say she's done.
这不是一件漂亮的东西吗
Ain't that a thing of beauty?
怀亚特
Wyatt!
进去
Get in!
你还和我们在一起吗
You still with us?
别管我
Less of me.
哇 哇
Whoa. Whoa.
麦卡蒂
Mccarty!
你死了吗
You dead yet?
当然没有
I sure ain't.
今天早上我没有看到
I'm assuming the fact I ain't seen
我的人达根
my man duggan this morning
这意味着他肯定和你有冲突
means he must have crossed paths with you,
事情未按他的方式进行
and things didn't go his way.
我刚刚在这里杀了你的人
Seeing as how I just killed your man al here,
对我们来说公平了
I'd say that squares us.
别再玩游戏了
No more games.
你有一分钟的时间出来
You got one minute to come out.
你差点害死我们俩
You nearly got us both killed,
你所有的眼泪和愤怒也差不多了
which is about all your tears and rage would have amounted to.
现在把头低下 你会没事的
Now keep your damn head down. You'll be all right.
低下头
Keep your head down,
你会没事的
you'll be all right.
波和麦金尼在门廊上
Poe and mckinney were on the porch.
加勒特闯进房子
Garrett went in the house.
开了两枪
Two shots...
但他
but he...
你对他们说西班牙语
And you were speaking Spanish to'em.
但他没有杀你
But he didn't kill you.
他帮你逃走了
He helped you escape.
你就是他
You're him.
他是谁
He's who?
邦尼
Bonney.
爸爸 他在说什么
Pa, what is he talking about?
比利小子 死了或活着
威廉·H·邦尼 更广为人知的名字是
比利小子
爸爸
Pa!
明智的选择 朋友
Smart choice, friend.
冷静点
为时已晚
这就是你的想法
我不知道 伙计
他在说什么
What's he saying?
你不要逞能出去
Don't you dare step outside.
没有人必须死
让我走
你可以留下钱
解下你的枪套
快点
你会送我进监狱吗
是警长的 没错吧
啊
Ah.
我不担心他
啊
Aah!
去你的
妈的
Fuck.
你没事吧
You all right?
噢
Oh.
怀亚特
Wyatt.
拿桶水和一些布来
Fetch a pail of water and some rags.
去吧
Go on.
你肯定见过更好的日子
You've certainly seen better days.
我知道你有一张熟悉的脸
I knew you had a familiar face.
一开始我还没意识到
I just couldn't place it at first.
我们会去找医生
We'll get the doc.
但首先要止住血
First I gotta slow the bleed.
这些年来 你是怎么躲起来的
How you manage to stay hidden all these years?
把衬衫袖子撕下来
Let's get some of this shirt off you.
用来绑住腿
I can use it to tie off this leg.
哦 该死
Well, shit.
我希望你没看见这事
I wish you didn't see that.
就像我之前听你告诉你儿子的一样
It's just like I heard you tell your boy before.
我没有撒谎
Ain't that I lied,
我只是没告诉你全部真相
I just never told you the whole truth.
你根本不是警察
Was you law at all?
伍兹郡的治安官 就如我所说
Sheriff of woods county, just like I said.
我和我的副手们在春天和凯彻姆签约
Me and my deputies, we signed on with ketchum back in the spring.
我们必须接受他们的指挥
We had to take their brand.
和他们一起做些事
Done a few jobs with'em.
但我们发现他们打算在最后一次行动中杀了我们
But we figured out they was planning to gun us down on this last go.
所以我们想先下手为强
So we tried to beat'em to the punch.
失败后 他们一直在追捕我
Took off, and they plugged me from a distance.
他们会追我到天涯海角
They'd have hunted me to the end of the earth.
很抱歉 我最后到了这里
I'm sorry I ended up here.
你想要的真相 是我最不愿做的事
Last thing I wanted, you wanna know the truth of it.
因为那时你对我很好
'Cause you were good to me back then.
呵
Huh.
我永远不会相信你做了他们说的那些事
I could never square you done the things they said.
虽然我现在确实可以相信
Though I sure as hell can believe it now.
我甚至不记得你了
I don't even remember you.
为什么要记得 我只是个农场工人
Well, why would you? I was just a ranch hand.
现在我要成为杀死比利小子的人了
Now I get to be the man who killed Billy the kid.
-坚持住 我去找医生 -不
-You hold on, I'll get the doc. -No.
爸爸
Pa.
我能走到今天是个奇迹
It's a miracle I made it this far.
一旦这消息传出
Once this gets out...
你会听到一些关于我的事
You gonna hear some things about me.
有些是真的
Some of it's true.
但很多都不是
A lot of it ain't.
实际上
Fact is...
我甚至都不知道我是谁或是什么了
I don't even know who or what I was anymore.
我不相信救赎
I don't believe in redemption.
但一个男人可以找到一些慰藉
But a man can find some kind of solace...
如果他有你这样的孩子要抚养
If he's got a boy like you to raise.
世界正在发生变化
The world is changing.
你去看看吧
You go see it.
这里不再是属于我的地方
It's a place I don't belong in no more.
我希望
I'm hoping...
你喜欢
You do.
爸爸
Pa?
走吧
Come on.
编剧 导演
帕塔西·蓬西罗里
音 乐
乔丹·莱宁
主 演
蒂姆·布雷克·尼尔森
斯科特·汉泽
主 演
加文·刘易斯
小理查德·斯佩特